https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/Add-ons/WebExtensions/Prompt_users_for_data_and_privacy_consents

Firefox editions
Firefox version and their web extension development capabilities
Basic workflow with no add-on ID
When do you need an add-on ID?
Request permissions at runtime
Add information about permissions to your extensions AMO page
6. Test, test, and then test again
What’s great content and design?
Set up a developer profile
Use plain language in any privacy policy or license agreement
Debug your extension
Developing extensions for Firefox for Android (Fennec)
Debug your extension
GeckoView Extensions (Android library)
Migration paths
Don't see the WebExtensions APIs you need?
Testing persistent and restart features
What is an add-on ID?
What is a Firefox profile?
Extension behavior in Firefox
What do I do to ensure I can test my extension?
Third Party Library Usage
When must links for third-party libraries be provided?
How to determine the third-party library link
Communicating third-party library links to reviewers
What does review rejection mean to users?
Make money from browser extensions
Will I ever be able to sell through AMO?
What can't you do
What can you do
Unsolicited offers
How can I maximize my income?
Community
Who is part of the community?
Firefox editions
Firefox version and their web extension development capabilities
Basic workflow with no add-on ID
When do you need an add-on ID?
Request permissions at runtime
Add information about permissions to your extensions AMO page
6. Test, test, and then test again
What’s great content and design?
Set up a developer profile
Use plain language in any privacy policy or license agreement
Debug your extension
Developing extensions for Firefox for Android (Fennec)
Debug your extension
GeckoView Extensions (Android library)
Migration paths
Don't see the WebExtensions APIs you need?
Testing persistent and restart features
What is an add-on ID?
What is a Firefox profile?
Extension behavior in Firefox
What do I do to ensure I can test my extension?
Third Party Library Usage
When must links for third-party libraries be provided?
How to determine the third-party library link
Communicating third-party library links to reviewers
What does review rejection mean to users?
Make money from browser extensions
Will I ever be able to sell through AMO?
What can't you do
What can you do
Unsolicited offers
How can I maximize my income?
Community
Who is part of the community?
Prompt users for data and privacy consents
If your extension uses cookies or collects user data, it needs to comply with the requirement of the Data Disclosure, Collection and Management section of the Add-on Policies.
A common developer question about these policies is how to translate them into web extension features that can pass the addons.mozilla.org reviews. This how-to is the result of those requests and offers advice on implementing prompts to meet the data collection and add-on policies. This article suggests how you can implement suitable prompts but it doesn’t replace or supersede the policies; you still need to confirm that your extension complies with the policies.
Contents
Know your privacy settingsGet preparedCreate a privacy policyPrompt after install or on first useDetermine your consent flowYour consent dialogs
Know your privacy settings
To create the consent flow and consent dialogues your extension needs, you should first answer these questions:
Does my extension use cookies?  If so, you’ll need to get user consent to store cookies.
Does my extension collect technical or interaction data? (If you’re unsure what technical and interaction data is, check out the definition in Data Disclosure, Collection and Management.) If so, offer the user the opportunity to opt-out of this data collection, although you can always offer opt-in consent if you prefer.
Does my extension collect personally identifying information? If so, get the user’s opt-in consent before collecting any of this data. Remember that personally identifying information includes technical or interaction data tagged with the user’s identity or information that can be used to identify the user, such as an IP address.
Get prepared
Before designing the data collection and use of cookies consents for your extension, you should:
eliminate any unnecessary data collection or cookies.
design your extension to offer as much functionality as possible if the user declines the collection of data or the use of cookies.
create a privacy policy.
Create a privacy policy
When your users arrive at your data and privacy consent dialogue, they need to know what they're consenting to and this is where your privacy policy comes in. The Data Disclosure, Collection and Management section of the Add-on Policies provides clear guidelines on what the policy should include. If you’re collecting significant quantities of data and making significant use of it, taking legal advice may be prudent. However, your first strategy should be to reduce or eliminate the collection of user data where possible. If your data collection and use is fairly low-level, it’s possible that privacy policy generator—such as Cooley LLP or iubenda—may be helpful. You may also want to take a look at Mozilla's privacy policy as a model to follow.
Prompt after install or on first use
As part of your extension’s onboarding flow, include information about your privacy policy and data collection, and seek any necessary user consents. Any privacy information and settings should be clear and unmissable, separating these details from general information about your extension can help.
For more information on how to implement a post-install page or dialog, see Best practices for onboarding, upboarding, and offboarding users.
As mentioned in the Add-on policies, if your extension uses cookies or collects user data in association with features that run in the background, such as ad blocking, you need to make sure the cookies or data collection are not activated until you have user consent.
We have talked about how you could let users opt-out of collecting technical and interaction data but must have users opt-in to collecting personally identifying information. Before you design your extension features around your consent requests, it is important to understand how these options affect your design.
Where you provide the user with an opt-in option, the related feature must be turned off by default and only turned on once the user has actively agreed to use that feature.
Where you provide the user with an opt-out, option the related features can be turned on by default but must be turned off if the user indicates they want to opt-out.
Determine your consent flow
Before designing your consent dialogs, you should determine the privacy consent flow for your extension, based on the data it collects and whether it uses cookies. Here is an example of a consent flow where an extension collects personally identifying information and technical data and uses cookies:
In this example:
Your extension should start up with all cookie and data collection functionality disabled.
Either shortly after installation (see Best practices for onboarding, upboarding, and offboarding users) or when the user first attempts to uses an extension feature, present them with a consent dialog.
On this dialog:
The option for collecting personally identifying information must default to disabled so that the user has to actively opt-in.
The options for technical data and cookies may default to enabled, so that the user may choose to opt-out.
If the user opts:
IN to all features, continue with all extension features enabled.
OUT of any feature that cannot be disabled, offer them the option to remove the extension. If they choose not to remove the extension present the consent dialog again.
OUT only from features that can be disabled, disable those features and continue running the extension.
Your consent dialogs
Once you understand your privacy consent flow, you can add suitable consent dialogues. The following are suggestions on how to present data collection and cookie consent dialogs. Where the mockups include the linked text “our Privacy Policy”, this should go to your extension’s privacy policy page on AMO. If you choose to follow these mockups, remember to modify them appropriately for your extension.
Only Cookies. The option to add cookies can be set as the default response.
Only personally identifying information. The default option is not to collect personally identifying information. If you do, the user needs to actively opt-in. Remember to list the data you’re collecting; don’t make the user read your privacy policy to determine what data you are collecting and why.
Only technical data, (no user identifiers). The option to collect technical data can be set as the default response.
Combination: Cookies, Personal, and Technical Data.
The extension won’t work without data or cookies. The default option is your choice.
Tags:
add-ons
extensions
how-to
privacy
ui
user-interface
ux
webextensions Contributors: rebloor Last update: rebloor Apr 24, 2019
Up Next
DevelopBuild an accessible extension
DevelopOnboard, upboard, offboard users
DevelopUser experience best practices
Documentation Topics
Develop
Publish
Manage
Enterprise
Themes
Connect With Us
Twitter
For developers:
@mozamo
For end users:
@rockyourfirefox
More
Matrix
Community forum
Extensions Developer Newsletter
Stay up-to-date on news and events for Firefox extension developers.
Email Address
I’m okay with Mozilla handling my info as explained in this Privacy Notice.
Sign up
Thanks! Please check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
If you haven’t previously confirmed a subscription to a Mozilla-related newsletter you may have to do so. Please check your inbox or your spam filter for an email from us.
